All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. What you just said. Today's דף
daf is ט"ו, Tet-Vav, fifteen. We pick up in the middle. We're
still maintaining a bit of a lead.
And we pick up where it says
רבינא
אמר. Ravina amar. לעולם, Le'olam, starting with the word לעולם. le'olam. It
is about fifteen lines from the bottom. So let me remind you
what's what's going on here. The משנה Mishna dealt with, having the
משנה Mishna at the end of the last פרק perek spoke about
somebody who said, "My mouth is forbidden like קונם פי מדבר עמך,"
Konam pi medaber imcha, which was a, it talked about speech but
focused on the physical body part of the mouth. And that that
worked because that was a נדר neder regarding a דבר שיש בו
ממש, davar sheyesh bo mamash, in a sense of the body part.
This משנה Mishna just speaks about a קונם konam that I won't,
regarding my, "קונם, konam, my sleeping is קונם. konam. My speech is
קונם," konam, which seems to be a דבר שאין בו ממש. davar
she'ein bo mamash. So that's number one in terms of the משנה.
Mishna. The גמרא, Gemara, however, started us off with a different issue.
A debate, and this is going to be a debate that's going
to take us till the end of, mostly till the end of
today, between רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav on the
one hand and רב נחמן Rav Nachman on the other. רב יהודה
אמר רב, Rav Yehuda amar Rav, and the question was: if somebody
basically says, "A נדר, neder, this thing is forbidden to me today
on the condition that I do or don't do something tomorrow," do
we let the person, quote unquote, "violate" potentially violate the נדר neder
today, trusting that that person will be able to ensure that the
תנאי tnai is not, you know, violated tomorrow? Or do we feel
that once tomorrow it's all about the תנאי, tnai, the person won't
treat that with the same type of weight they would in terms
of violating the נדר? neder? Even though that violation, I'm going to
call it violating the תנאי tnai out of simplicity. I mean, you
could say fulfilling the תנאי, tnai, but I think my point is
being triggering the conditions under which the נדר neder will take effect.
Okay, so therefore we could say that, you know, whatever, if you
trigger those conditions, if you violate the תנאי, tnai, retroactively you violated
the נדר, neder, which is true, but it's all retroactive, it's in
the past, and maybe you won't take it so seriously. So that's
the debate. רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav says that
we don't allow you to do it to violate today because you
will not take it seriously tomorrow. You won't take the תנאי tnai
as serious as you would the vow. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says you will take the תנאי tnai as serious as you would
the vow. So that's the debate. And we tried to try to
sort of say that our משנה Mishna about sleeping was that special
case of, you know, what I'm going to do today based on,
dependent on what I do tomorrow, which is a really forced read
of the משנה. Mishna. But you know, the גמרא Gemara does that
sometimes. It takes a משנה Mishna which says, maybe is pretty obvious,
and let's try to say it's talking about our case. Anyway, one
of the reasons the גמרא Gemara said that the משנה Mishna was
obvious was it was sort of like a ממה נפשך. mimanshach. If
the משנה Mishna is that I am making my sleep as an
abstract idea forbidden, then it wouldn't work. And if it's I'm making
my eyes forbidden to sleep, then we already taught that in a
previous משנה. Mishna. So therefore it said, so since it can't be
one or the other, it's got to be our our particular case
of a תנאי. tnai. That's where we left off. And then the
גמרא Gemara here has now a different answer, which is very important,
before we get back to this debate of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
and רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. And the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says, לעולם, Le'olam, so again, line
starts with the word לעולם, le'olam, it's about fifteen lines from the
bottom. לעולם כדקתני. Le'olam kedekatani.
Our משנה Mishna says like it sounds like, that you actually made
the נדר neder קונם, konam, the sleep itself. So how could it
say there's בל
יחל?
bal
yachel? It's a דבר שאין בו ממש. davar she'ein bo mamash. ומאי
בל יחל מדרבנן? Umai bal yachel mi-derabbanan? מדרבנן, Mi-derabbanan, here very important
point, which we said in passing before, that even though נדר neder
only takes effect on something physical, it can take also effect on
something abstract מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan. So my sleep is קונם, konam, my walking
is קונם. konam. So therefore, you know, the big difference between action
and person and object a little bit falls away, conceptually not, because
there's still a difference between saying a שבועה shvuah I won't walk,
and saying my walking is קונם. konam. Right? One is still the
conceptual, the, you know, the abstract idea of walking, whereas the other
is about me, the person. But nevertheless, a lot of the practical
differences will fall, you know, you know, it does collapse some of
those differences. All right? So therefore we're saying that yes, our משנה
Mishna is not a special case of תנאי tnai and the חידוש
chiddush of our משנה Mishna is even though you make the נדר
neder just in terms of the walking and not your legs, it
still takes effect מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan. ומאי בל יחל מדרבנן. Umai bal yachel
mi-derabbanan. So the גמרא Gemara says: ומי איכא בל יחל מדרבנן? Umi
ika bal yachel mi-derabbanan? Would there ever be something, "בל יחל," bal
yachel, which is a you shall not let his vow be violated,
would we use it on a מדרבנן? derabbanan? Now, does that mean
that the גמרא Gemara thinks that there are no נדרים מדרבנן? nedarim
mi-derabbanan? No, I mean there's plenty of evidence that the גמרא Gemara
is okay with saying that there are, you know, we'll make a
מדרבנן derabbanan things on a נדר. neder. Thank you so much. The
issue is about presumably whether we would use the phrase of בל
יחל, bal yachel, which is a... פסוק *pasuk* in the תורה *Torah*.
Like would somebody say that if you ate chicken with meat, you're
עובר over *over* on, a chicken with milk, you're עובר *over* on
לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו *lo tivashal gedi be-halev imo*? No, you'd
say it's אסור assur מדרבנן m'drabbanan. *asur mi-derabbanan*. So are you going
to use a פסוק *pasuk* of בל יחל Bal Yachel *bal yachel*
on something that's only a דרבנן d'rabonon. *derabbanan*? That's the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s question. Okay, if this idea of the abstract action is a
object is like a, you know, at least on a דרבנן d'rabonon.
*derabbanan* level, would we say בל יחל Bal Yachel *bal yachel*? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אין *in*, yes, ותניא *ve-hatanya* we taught
in a ברייתא braita *Baraita*: דברים המותרים ואחרים נהגו בהן איסור issur.
*devarim ha-muttarim va-aherim nahagu bahen issur*, if something is permissible and other
people are treating it with a practice of treating it as forbidden,
that there's a מנהג minhag. *minhag* not to do certain things or
eat certain things, then so אי אתה רשאי להתירן בפניהם *i attah
rashai le-hattiran bifnehem*, you cannot tell them, ah, you know, this is
just a crazy מנהג minhag, *minhag*, really what you guys are doing
is really totally okay, it's permissible, שנאמר לא יחל דברו devaro *she-ne'emar
lo yachel devaro*, because it says your word should not be, the
word should not be violated. So meaning that meaning that
they are bound by their practice, and nobody thinks that this is
a real נדר neder *neder*. Now this is really important, right, because
again we keep on going back to sort of like the whole
idea of התרת נדרים nedarim *hattarat nedarim*. We have a whole מסכת
masechet *masechet* here that's about a נדר neder, *neder* in terms of
making objects forbidden, but the נדר neder *neder* that we know, right,
when somebody says like בלי נדר neder *bli neder*, right, we've talked
about this today, you really sort of mean like בלי שבועה shvua,
*bli shvua*. You know, the נדר neder? *neder* we know most of
all often is when we're talking about like committing to do a
certain thing. So as we said, that's like this concept of נדרי
מצווה mitzvah *nidrei mitzvah*, אשנה השנה פרק זה *ashne ha-shana perek ze*,
if you remember, and even there some ראשונים Rishonim *rishonim* said it
really meant שבועה shvua *shvua*, not נדר neder *neder*. Okay, but that
was this idea like we've been saying, the biblical idea of נדר
neder *neder*, וידור יעקב נדר neder לאמור *vayiddor Yaakov neder lemor* is
obligate yourself to do something and then it translates into giving something.
So it both has that personal obligation and that object. But, you
know, often for us the concept of נדר neder *neder* we focus
on is that sense of a personal religious type of an obligation
that we accept upon ourselves, right? And one of the classic examples
we do, like what we say in the התרת נדרים nedarim *hattarat
nedarim*, is, you know, כל דבר טוב davar tov. שנהגתי שלוש פעמים
ולא אמרתי שיהא דבר זה בלי נדר neder *kol davar tov she-nahagti
shalosh pe'amim ve-lo amarti she-ye-he davar ze bli neder*, that somehow by
doing some type of a מצווה mitzvah *mitzvah* action, again not technical
מצווה mitzvah *mitzvah* obligation because then it wouldn't be a נדר neder
*neder* related, but some type of a positive religious action practice three
times in a row becomes like a קבלת נדר neder *kabbalat neder*
to do this on an ongoing basis. It's actually quite interesting that
the חתם סופר *Hatam Sofer*, who you know spent a lot of
effort combating Reform Judaism and combating the idea of like introducing any
changes into practice, so one of the big ways that you can
combat any change in practice, even if it's הלכתית *halachically* justified, is
basically saying well it's אסור assur *asur* because, you know, it's not
our מנהג minhag *minhag* to do this. You know, the מנהג minhag
*minhag* is that we don't do this type of a thing. Of
course the problem with that is like okay, you know, like מנהגים
minhagim. *minhagim* change, you know, but that's not that doesn't sound to
me like such an overwhelmingly strong argument if something is הלכתית *halachically*
permissible.
But the ability to use מנהג minhag, *minhag* is a very powerful
tool from a small-c conservative, you know, from a conservatism approach because
just as things have to be kept the way they've been, that,
you know, these are our practices. So what the חתם סופר *Hatam
Sofer* did to bolster the whole argument of מנהג minhag, *minhag* was
he basically said that, yeah, because every מנהג minhag *minhag* is basically
a נדר neder *neder* to act this way. So every מנהג minhag
*minhag* becomes like a דאורייתא D'Oraisa. *de-oraita*. There's even one תשובה *tshuva*
where he basically I think he's talking about some question about using,
you know, milk of non-Jews or whatever, or and this is milk
or no, it might be a בישול עכו"ם *bishul akum* case. Anyway,
he says look, he says so there's this question whether the fact
that we don't do this particular thing, you know, if it falls
in the דרבנן drabbanan. *derabbanan* category or not. He says but even
if it doesn't fall he says so even if it falls into
the דרבנן drabbanan *derabbanan* category and it's אסור assur דרבנן drabbanan *asur
derabbanan*, or it doesn't fall in the דרבנן d'rabbanans, *derabbanan* category and
therefore it's just because of a מנהג minhag *minhag*, and that would
make it a דאורייתא *de-oraita* because of נדר neder *neder*.
So you have the ability, the idea of using this idea of
a נדר neder *neder*, you know, anytime you do a particular practice.
Anyway, fine. So there's but that is what? Well, okay, that's an
interesting question. Anyway, I point all of that because that becomes such
this big, you know, category of thinking about נדרים nedarim *nedarim* in
terms of personal religious practices that we've adopted and מנהגים minhagim, *minhagim*
and so on. And it's almost completely absent right from our מסכת
*masechet*, which completely focuses on the power of נדר neder *neder* in
terms of relating to objects. Okay, but a little hint here and
there and a statement here and a statement there, you know, it
winds up getting to become a very like powerful idea. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is introducing here, that there's an idea
of בל יחל Bal Yachel *bal yachel* if people have a religious
practice, even though הלכתית *halachically* it's permissible, you don't go ahead and
say, ah, you don't have to do that. No, לא יחל דברו
*lo yachel devaro*. Now what does it mean בל יחל דברו Bal
Yachel Devaro *bal yachel devaro*? Does that mean like if somebody again
were to be violating a particular religious practice, you know, going against
it, they would be עובר *over* on בל יחל Bal Yachel *bal
yachel*, you know, at least
a דרבנן בל יחל d'rabonon Bal Yachel, *derabbanan bal yachel*? The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says... somebody else's thing that somebody else, you know, an
important religious practice another person is doing. So you, like it's the
you, the other person, don't be יחל דברו of that person, that
person's actions. And that would be like a little bit more of
like a rhetorical point, right, as opposed to you shouldn't go against
a practice you've adopted. What?
Oh, that's the understanding for all חומרות, chumros, for all מנהגים. minhagim
Right,
exactly. Why would you have someone not violate someone else's?
No, the point is you don't go, you know, it's not your
place to go ahead and tell somebody you don't have to worry
about a particular religious practice. בל יחל
Bal
Yachel in that way?
Right, that's what I mean it as a rhetorical point. Don't you
think, oh, I'm going to set them all straight. That's their practice,
you don't go ahead violating things that they've adopted. That I think
might be the פשט pshat here, more of a rhetorical point. But
the גמרא Gemara is using it more like as a technical הלכה's
Halacha point that there's a בל יחל מדרבנן. Bal Yachel mi-d'rabonon. And
then that presumably would mean that they're not allowed to sort of
violate their own מנהג. And that gets this idea that if you
adopt a particular מנהג, you know, the relationship of מנהג and נדר
neder and so on. One more point and then I'll take your
question, which is, so it seems that the גמרא's Gemara argument is
like by analogy. The same way if you have a certain religious
מנהג it becomes a type of a דרבנן בל יחל, Bal Yachel
so similarly we made an idea that if you say נדר, neder
sleeping עלי, alai, that's not the same as a religious מנהג, that's
נדר neder, my sleeping on me, קונם konam my sleeping on me,
but we also made another rabbinic category of נדר neder that it
could take effect on these abstract ideas and not necessarily on concrete
objects. That's the simple read. That's an argument by analogy. Interestingly תוספות
Tosafot says that if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says
like this,
he says, three lines from the bottom, וכן נהגו בו איסור תימא
מה עניין זה לנהגו בו איסור. v'achen nahagu bo issur teima mah
inyan zeh l'nahagu bo issur. ויש
לומר דהאי נמי שנדר ונתכוין לאסור עצמו גם בדבר שאין בו ממש,
v'yesh lomar d'hai namei she-nadar v'nitkaven l'esor atzmo gam b'davar she-ein bo
mamash, if you're trying to forbid yourself let's say on something like
sleeping, right,
אין לך מנהג גדול מזה. ein lecha minhag gadol mi-zeh. כעין למשיח—it
k'mein l'mashiach doesn't mean the Messiah, it means מורי שיחיה. mori she-yichye.
Okay. So anyway, so what he is saying is it's not by
analogy, it's the same thing. If I say קונם konam sleeping עלי,
alai, then that's נהגו בו איסור, nahagu bo issur, because I'm trying
to make it a דבר אסור, davar assur, which is funny, it's
not the פשט, pshat, right? The פשט pshat is that's not נהגו
בו איסור. nahagu bo issur. נהגו בו איסור nahagu bo issur means
you have a pattern of a certain type of a religious practice.
So he tries to make them the same, but more simply it's
an argument by analogy. The last point I'll make and then I'll
take Michael's question is that there's also different types of מנהגים, minhagim
right? There are מנהגים minhagim which are like pro, which are like
active things, like a מנהג, I don't know, to שלוג כפרות shlog
kapparos on ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. Okay, would you call
that also a type of a בל יחל bal yachal and a
נדר? neder. Right, when we say נהגתי דבר טוב שנהגתי שלוש פעמים,
nahagti davar tov she-nahagti shalosh pe'amim, that's like I don't know, I
would spend every Friday, every שבת Shabbos afternoon going and doing ביקור
חולים bikur cholim at the hospital. Right, that would be a דבר
טוב. That's not exactly, that's even more different from our נדר neder
types of discussions. The language of this ברייתא is דברים המותרים ואכן
נהגו בהן איסור. devarim ha-muttarim v'achen nahagu bahen issur. So now it
actually is much more similar if you read that narrowly. It's saying
we treat something as a דבר אסור. davar assur. So for example
let's say somebody says like, I don't know,
chicken and milk.
Right, well okay, but that's דרבנן. That's דרבנן. Okay, but
let's say for example somebody says, I'm not going to eat bacon
bits, kosher, kosher bacon bits. I'm not going to eat, right, like
a, I don't eat on פסח, Pesach, I don't like all of
this חמץ chametz taste, feel, feeling stuff. I'm not going to eat
any of this potato starch sponge cakes on פסח. Pesach. Okay, so
that's נהגו בו איסור. nahagu bo issur. We're talking specifically about an
איסור. issur Therefore you can see that that becomes like a, it's
much more similar to the world of נדרים nedarim because then it
relates to maybe objects, right, or even if it relates to actions,
I you know, I don't know, I'm not going to go on
any, you know, the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim talks about מנהגים
about people that would not go on any like trip on Friday
because they didn't want to get, you know, be late on שבת.
Shabbos. Okay, so what you're נוהג איסור noheg issur in going on
the trips, so that becomes like our idea of this abstract thing,
going on trips on Friday, if you think of that as like
not a concrete thing but an abstract thing, that thing, that going
on the trips, that is a דבר אסור davar assur to me.
So then actually it is important to know that when we talk
about נהגו בו איסור, nahagu bo issur, whether we're talking about objects
or actions, then it is much more similar to the world of
נדרים nedarim. and much more similar to the idea of דבר שאין
בו ממש. davar she-ein bo mamash. Now Michael, you had a question.
Yeah, my question was this, I mean just read in the actual,
you know, where this... you say יצא השדיא דשיחן מפניהם yatza hashdaya
desichan mipnehem does it
mean like
you know I can't say like alright you don't need to do
it or do we even say like extend so far as I
can't even tell them like מנהג היתר? minhag heter?
No no that's a different question.
That's about מקום שהלכו
makom shehalchu vs מקום שיצאו משם makom sheyatzu misham that we're not
talking about. I mean that might be true but that's not the
conversation right now.
We're talking about
we can't tell them it's okay. Right. Okay yeah.
So is there a difference between חומרא chumra or just אסור assur
in something in the וועלט? velt?
Yeah maybe I mean if you're just saying I'm חושש choshesh for
a certain הלכה halakha position that's not exactly the same as נהגו
בו היתר. nahagu bo heter. Right. All of this like I said
becomes that whole big category of like adopting practices upon yourselves and
becoming נדרים nedarim and again you know you learn מסכת נדרים Masechet
Nedarim and you assume that's what we're talking about. But no then
you realize we're also talking about like making objects forbidden. So again
the degree to which you get something like that if we're talking
about like a positive act that's more like the you know אשכם
ושנה פרק זה ashchem v'shana perek zeh discussion right and if you're
talking about making certain things forbidden that's what we have נהגו בו
איסור nahagu bo issur which might be more close to the world
of נדרים Nedarim, we've been discussing but again the גמרא Gemara says
it's מדרבנן. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara. says like this
okay תנן tnan we're still not done with our debate of רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda and רב נחמן Rav Nachman about whether we think
you can violate the נדר neder if we trust you and we'll
trust you not to violate the תנאי. tnai. So let's take a
look we got a משנה mishna coming up a little in like
about a month. שאת נהנית לי עד הפסח אם תלכי לבית אביך
עד החג.
she'at nehenis li ad HaPesach
im telchi l'veis avicha ad HeChag. So מן אביך man avich thank
you. So a man makes a נדר against his wife and says
you cannot derive any benefit from me from
פסח Pesach if you go to visit your father's house anytime up
through סוכות. Succos. Now again we're assuming that פסח Pesach is going
to come first the order of the חגים chagim is פסח Pesach
comes first okay so let's use should we draw this?
I think it's pretty clear but never hurts to use the board.
Okay so let's say let's say here's ניסן Nissan right and here's
תשרי Tishrei okay here's סוכות Succos
here's פסח Pesach
they're standing over here
like that okay very traditional anyway what he yeah okay fine how
come he's bald?
Okay גברא gavra enough enough he says right no הנאה hana'ah you
can't get any הנאה hana'ah from me okay that's the הנאה hana'ah
part from till פסח Pesach if you go to בית אביך beis
avicha that's the תנאי tnai right any of this time so okay
what's הנאה hana'ah mean?
מזונות mezonos sex?
Whatever
let's say sex okay we'll get to that anyway all right so
anyway here's the point that during the period from now till פסח
Pesach right if she actually triggered the תנאי tnai violated the תנאי
tnai she would know that she can't get הנאה hana'ah right? But
if she hasn't gone to her father's house and she's in this
period can she be getting הנאה hana'ah from him? Will we say
it's okay to get הנאה hana'ah from your husband and we'll trust
you not to go to your father's house or not? That's the
question of רב נחמן Rav Nachman and רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda would say don't get any הנאה hana'ah from your
husband here cause we won't be able to trust you not to
go to your father's house and רב נחמן Rav Nachman would say
no problem get הנאה hana'ah from your husband just be careful afterwards.
So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says.
Alright we're not going to worry about that now. Okay so the
גמרא Gemara so the משנה mishna says like this הלכה לפני הפסח
halcha lifnei haPesach
if she went to her father's house before פסח Pesach okay אסורה
בהנאתו עד הפסח assura behana'aso ad haPesach so now she's triggered the
תנאי tnai and she can't get הנאה. hana'ah. Okay that's pretty straightforward
now let's see what the גמרא Gemara infers from this. הלכה לפני
הפסח אסורה halcha lifnei haPesach assura
only if she's gone before פסח Pesach do we say don't get
now don't get הנאה hana'ah from your husband until פסח Pesach לא
הלכה לא lo halcha lo if you haven't yet gone to your
father's house
you're able to get הנאה hana'ah from your husband we'll just trust
you not to trigger the תנאי tnai later. So אמר רבי אבא
amar Rabbi Abba no that's not what it means it means הלכה
לפני הפסח halcha lifnei haPesach if she's already gone to her father's
house and it's before פסח Pesach אסורה ולוקה assura v'loka now the
תנאי tnai has been triggered and she's definitely forbidden and now she
would get הנאה hana'ah we know she's violated the נדר and there'd
be lashes. לא הלכה lo halcha if she didn't go to her
father's house and it's this period up to פסח Pesach so we
don't know what's going to be the story with this period whether
the תנאי tnai will be triggered or not then אסורה בעלמא assura
b'alma she's just simply forbidden. Okay so when it says if she's
gone to her father's house here don't derive benefit really she's not
allowed to derive benefit either way because we don't know what's going
to happen later but it's what it says. If you've triggered the
תנאי tnai *tenai* and don't derive—it's clearly now it's in force, don't
derive benefit, if so, you'll get lashes. If you haven't yet triggered
the תנאי tnai *tenai*, then רב יהודה Rav Yehuda. *Rav Yehuda* would
say, I still don't want you to derive benefit because I won't
trust you to be careful with the תנאי tnai *tenai*, but it
won't be as weighty because you don't yet know that it's going
to be in violation, okay? So although the משנה Mishna *Mishna* says,
don't violate after you've triggered the תנאי Tnai *tenai*, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda, *Rav Yehuda* would say don't even violate before you've triggered the
תנאי Tnai *tenai*, I won't trust you to be careful with the
תנאי Tnai, *tenai*, but nevertheless it won't be as severe, we won't
know yet that you've violated and even if you did violate retroactively
you won't get lashes because you know like it'll be like התראת
ספק *hatra'at safek*.
Yes? So I don't remember, is there such a thing as a
שבועה shvua בתנאי *shvua bitnai*? Yes, but we haven't dealt with it
yet.
תנאי Tnai. *tenai* in this case... so that's just so interesting to
me because
I mean any שבועה *shvua* that I won't get הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*
if I do this.
Right, but there you have a concern of also taking the שם
שמים לבטלה *Shem Shamayim l'vatala*, no?
Yeah, but we don't in general by a שבועה *shvua* it's not—it's
a concern of violating the שבועה *shvua*, not—not the using God's name,
then you would never be able to take any שבועה *shvua*, okay,
but we—yeah, but we—yes?
Same I'm thinking through this, you know, I mean maybe a little
bit different with a husband and wife or whatever because you know
he—she—whatever just
given their relationship and the two but if you say to me
like you know you can't have הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* from me if
you go I don't know whatever across the street you know for
a month whatever, right? And then so I can say okay well
you know don't give me anything and you know like in other
words it's your objects why would I be getting lashes?
Alright so that's an excellent question, I'm going to get back to
that in a minute. Alright, excellent, who gets lashes? Okay, hold off
on that, that's a really central question. I'm going to finish the
גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* discussion on this משנה Mishna *Mishna* and then we're
going to go back to that question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. אימא סיפא *Eima seifa*, let's look at the
end of this משנה Mishna *Mishna*. אחר הפסח בבל יחל bivyal yachel.
דברו *Achar haPesach b'val yachel devaro*, if she went to her father's
house after פסח Pesach *Pesach*, she's transgressed בל יחל bal yachal *bal
yachel*. Okay, so what's the scenario that she's over on בל יחל
bal yachal *bal yachel* if she went to her father's house after
פסח Pesach. *Pesach*? Must be she got הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* before פסח
Pesach, *Pesach*, right? And then she went after פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, she
triggers the תנאי Tnai. *tenai* and retroactively she's done בל יחל *bal
yachel*. ואי דלא איתהני *V'ee d'lo it'hani*, if she never got הנאה
hana'ah *hana'ah* לפני הפסח *lifnei haPesach* before פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, מי איכא
בל יחל *mi itka bal yachel*? So there's no בל יחל *bal
yachel*. אלא פשיטא דאיתהני *Ela p'shita d'it'hani*, it must be she got
הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*. אלמא איתהני *alma it'hani*, you see you're allowed to
get הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*. Okay, so basically the משנה mishnah, *Mishna* says
if she went afterwards then retroactively she's over on בל יחל *bal
yachel*, but that implies that it had no problem with her getting
הנאה hana'ah. *hana'ah* during this period. It don't—it doesn't say don't get
הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*. It says if you trigger the תנאי Tnai, *tenai*,
don't get הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*. And if you went afterwards retroactively you're
over. It's—so it sounds like it has no problem before she's triggered
the תנאי Tnai. *tenai* with her getting הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*. It's just
telling her fine you haven't triggered it, get הנאה hana'ah, *hana'ah*, but
just don't trigger it now and if so retroactively you'll get—you'll be
over on בל יחל *bal yachel*. So since it says if you
trigger it here you're retroactively over on בל יחל *bal yachel* and
it never told her not to get הנאה hana'ah. *hana'ah*, it sounds
like it's okay with her getting הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*, it'll trust her
not to trigger the תנאי Tnai. *tenai*. If she does trigger the
תנאי Tnai *tenai* then retroactively she'll be over. So that's a contradiction
to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda*. ותיובתא דרב יהודה *V'tiyuvta d'Rav
Yehuda*, that's a contradiction on רב יהודה Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda* because
it seems like it's fine with her actually getting the הנאה hana'ah
*hana'ah*. No, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, כי תני דאי
איתהני *ki tani d'ee it'hani*, הרי זה בבל יחל דברו תנן Tnan
*harei zeh b'val yachel devaro t'nan*. No, it doesn't—it never says she's
allowed to get הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah*. It says—it basically it's not discussing
whether she's allowed or not. Okay, it's saying you know and saying
if she got הנאה hana'ah, *hana'ah* here and she triggers it here
retroactively she's over בל יחל *bal yachel*. In a way you could
actually read the משנה mishnah *Mishna* to say she's not allowed. The
משנה *Mishna* could be saying since if you trigger the תנאי Tnai
*tenai* here retroactively you'll be over on בל יחל *bal yachel*, then
the implicit message is therefore don't get הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* during this
point. So it doesn't discuss whether you're allowed or not allowed. It
discusses in practice if you trigger it here you'll be over retroactively
on בל יחל *bal yachel*. Whether or not you should or shouldn't
get הנאה hana'ah. *hana'ah* during this point is not being addressed and
maybe you shouldn't and maybe it's—it's telling you if you did here's
what's going to happen. Okay, but it's not clear whether or not
you're allowed. Now so the issue of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda. *Rav
Yehuda* and רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* is not resolved. Now
I want to go back to the question that's being asked which
is about who gets lashes. He made the vow, she got הנאה
hana'ah *hana'ah*, why should she get lashes for some type of a
thing that he's deciding to throw around all of these נדרים Nedarim.
*nedarim* and make her life impossible and now she's the one that
all of a sudden is burdened by that and is going to
get lashes. So if you take a look, the ר"ן Ran *Ran*
has a very important discussion about this. Let's turn back to עמוד
א' *amud aleph* and read the ר"ן Ran *Ran*.
Okay, הכא *hacha* that's about ten lines before the lines get wide
or ten lines from the bottom about twelve lines from the bottom.
אסור assur בהנאה behana'ah. ולוקה *asur b'hana'ah v'lokeh*. כלו כלומר
*klomar* ולוקה *ve-loka* we're going to see. כלומר *klomar* well לוקה lokeh.
*loka* according to that לוקה lokeh היא *loka hi* she gets lashes.
אבל איהו *Aval ihu* אינו לוקה *eino loke* שהרי לא עשה שום
איסור issur *she-harei lo asah shum issur*. He didn't do anything else
שהדירה *she-hedirah* he made a vow but she's the one who violated
it. דתנא נמי השמיענו מאגב אורחיה *De-tana nami hashmi’enu me-agav orchei* maybe
that's part of the point of this משנה *Mishnah* דעלה רכיב איסורא
*de-alah rechiv issura* that on her is the prohibition אבל לא עליו
כלל *aval lo alav klal* not on him. אבל הרמב"ם ז"ל כתב
*Aval ha-Rambam zal katav* לוקה הוא שהדירה *loke hu she-hedirah* he gets
lashes. Now not if he just passively did nothing, אם הנהנה אותה
*im he-henah otah* if he basically caused her to get
הנאה *hana'ah*. So he gave her a back rub or something I
don't know.
He directly caused her to get הנאה *hana'ah* then he has violated
his נדר *neder*. So then he is the one that has violated.
Anyway אבל היא אינה
לוקה *aval hi eina loka* she doesn't get lashes דכיון דלא נדרה
כלל *de-kivan de-lo nadrah klal* she didn't make a נדר *neder*. לא
שייך בה לא יחל דברו *Lo shayach bah lo yachel devaro*. She's
not violating her words. It says if you take a נדר *neder*
then you buddy who took a נדר *neder* don't violate your נדר
*neder*. This isn't her נדר *neder* so even if she goes against
it she has not violated.
Did he
do anything wrong at all? It doesn't say. Maybe it's לפני עיוור
*lifnei iver* on him. וליתא *Ve-leita* it's not true דודאי הוא אינו
לוקה *de-vadai hu eino loke* he doesn't get lashes מדאמרינן לקמן בפרק
אין בין המודר *mid’amrinan lekaman be-perek ein bein ha-mudar* גבי יש מילה
בקונמות *gabai yesh milah
be-konamos*.
So he proves it based on a סוגיא sugya *sugya* we haven't
seen. We're going to skip that a little bit. Anyway then I
want to just skip to the key line of what he does
with the words לא יחל דברו *lo yachel devaro* and then he
says like this אלמא *almah* the last narrow line אין האוסר עובר
כלל *ein ha-oser over klal*. The one who creates the איסור *issur*
does not violate
if the other person is the one who transgressed it. והמודר נמי
ודאי עבר *Veha-mudar nami vadai avar*
and the one who was the passive the one who the נדר
*neder* was taken against is the one who transgresses. דאף על גב
דכתיב d'chtiv לא יחל דברו *De-af al gav di-ketiv lo yachel devaro*
do not violate your word. לא יחל אדיבור קאמר *Lo yachel a-dibur
ka-amar*. The word, talk about an abstract idea, the word cannot be
violated. It doesn't really matter whose word it is, the word cannot
be violated. So if I say קונם Konam *konam* coffee זה על
מיכאל *zeh al Michael* so now my word has created the נדר
*neder* that's the whole point of נדר *neder*. My word has created
this status of the coffee and now מיכאל *Michael* would now violate
the status of that coffee that's been created. So that would be
a לא יחל *lo yachel*. It's not just me going against what
I said I would do. The גזירת נדר *gezeirat neder* is like
a שבועה *shvua* to do something. I promised to do something, I
have to live up to it. I can't violate and not live
up to what I obligated myself to do. This is conceptually in
the תורה *Torah* that's really what's going on because the נדר *neder*
is to do something as we've been discussing. But once the נדר
*neder* means an object then you get to this weird question. It's
not about me, it's about what I created in the object. So
if that word
basically created a status in the object somebody who would violate it
would violate that status is like violating that word. Violating my word,
but now you've violated it. That's a status that I've created. Now
I could
sanctify my animal as a קרבן korban *korban* and if you misuse
it you violate.
I can do my coffee on you. To me make something forbidden
on somebody else it has to be my stuff has to be
forbidden on somebody else. So
anyway but that is really... so you understand what the ר"ן Ran,
*Ran* says is totally consistent with the emphasis of the מסכת *Masechet*
which is on נדר *neder* creating a status in an object. And
it does make sense if the person who crosses the line that
shouldn't be crossed is the one who transgresses even though they didn't
draw that line in the sand they're the one who crossed that
line. הרמב"ם *Rambam* interestingly and again maybe this connects to a point
we made yesterday
about where the הרמב"ם *Rambam* says דבר הנדור *davar ha-nadur* it's not
enough that it's a status you create about objects it has to
be the types of things that you can actually give as a
free will offering to God. So the הרמב"ם *Rambam* actually says that
a חטאת *chatas* and an אשם *asham* are only very barely in
the דבר הנדור *davar ha-nadur* category because you can freely obligate yourself
to give them through becoming like a נזיר *nazir* but the point
is that for the הרמב"ם *Rambam* he doesn't totally shift our focus
to the objects. He still reminds us of the classic נדר *neder*
which is obligating yourself to give something to God. And therefore the
הרמב"ם *Rambam* basically says that it's the one who took the vow
who did it that's the person who's really commanded against violating that
vow. Now again does it mean it's permissible? We're talking here about
lashes. Could be that that yes he's not denying the fact that
this object now has an objective reality that I've created and somebody
who violates that reality would violate but they wouldn't get the lashes.
Okay and if I passively don't violate I make this forbidden and
Michael goes I wasn't בל יחל דברו he was being מחיל mechil
my דיבור. dibur. So neither of us gets lashes. He doesn't get
lashes cause it wasn't his דיבור dibur even though he did the
action and I don't get lashes cause I wasn't the one who
violated.
So wait what kind of case is that?
I say this coffee is אסור assur on Michael and Michael comes
and drinks it. Right? So according to the רמב"ם Rambam I don't
get lashes cause I didn't violate and he doesn't get lashes cause
it wasn't his word.
So they only get lashes if you said it'd
be אסור assur on you and you violated? Right the only or
if I held you down and poured the coffee down your throat
like הנאתה hana'ata then I am the one who violated my vow.
So for the רמב"ם Rambam to get lashes you need both: that
the status of the object be violated and it be the vow
of the person who's violating. That's what you need for lashes. If
you have one or the other we might still be talking about
that it's biblically prohibited doesn't have to jump to a rabbinic idea
but it's not the classic where you get the lashes. So again
according to the ר"ן Ran right according to the ר"ן Ran it's
all about the status of the object whoever violates the status is
עובר on בל יחל דברו the possessive of the דברו the ו
vav will bracket לא יחל הדיבור. Lo Yachel Hadibur. Okay and anybody
who violates it gets lashes. For the רמב"ם Rambam you need the
one who made the vow to violate the vow in order for
him to get lashes. Yes?
So wait how are we struggling, in this case we're not talking
about a חפץ cheftza we're talking about a תנאי Tnai. and a
מעשה. maaseh.
No the חפץ cheftza would be well this is also the question
about הנאה as an abstract entity so we might be talking about
a דרבנן. But it might be talking about like his body like
you know my body is אסור assur to you בהנאה. Okay so
it's true here I mean we're talking about הנאה from the person
and it might be a more דרבנן בל יחל because what you're
really prohibiting is the הנאה and not the object. But it could
be the object is the man's body. Right? So but yeah we
haven't gotten back to the physical to that aspect of this. Yes
David?
If the man makes this נדר and then he causes her like
you said give her a backrub or something like that. Right. Then
two things one if she visits her father after פסח Pesach, he's
not actually violating his vow she is.
Well he triggered the תנאי Tnai to cause then it's you're right
it gets complicated then yeah.
And the other thing is also then it's a constant interesting shift
of who's in control.
Right. Because she's in control of the תנאי Tnai. and he's in
control of that's a good point
that's a good point. I mean so for the רמב"ם Rambam you
know you're saying he might not get lashes because in the end
he didn't control the violation even though he did the violation she
in the end made it into a violation retroactively. Right that's a
good point so that does make that a special case. Yes Dov?
I could take a נדר not that like all coffee will be
אסור assur to me. Right. Like I don't own that coffee but
can I take a can I
make a נדר that all coffee will be אסור assur to you?
No no. So you can make your stuff אסור assur to other
people other people's stuff אסור assur to you you can't make other
people's stuff אסור assur to them. Okay. Okay yeah. What do we
I mean
we didn't say this but what happens if it's done בשוגג? beshogeg?
Is there any punishment for that?
Yeah
like any other בשוגג. beshogeg.
Do they bring a קרבן for instance?
No it's a לאו. lav. It's a לאו. lav. Okay so back
now to the גמרא. Gemara So very important I mean there's a
lot of like it's so funny how radically some of these דפים
dappim change. We went from a דף daf on שבת Shabbat with
the הקרבן Hakorban כקרבן Kakorban לקרבן Lakorban or whatever which like your
head was swimming. And now in today's דף daf right think about
all the important things we've talked about. We've talked about a דרבנן
of בל יחל on not just objects but on abstract ideas entities
actions and so on that there's could be a בל יחל דרבנן.
Bal Yachel drabbanan. We discussed the idea of בל יחל by מנהגים
okay at least by a מנהג of איסור as opposed to a
מנהג of היתר. hetter. מנהג of איסור fits a little bit more
into that category. And now we've discussed the question that you would
think somewhere in this מסכת the גמרא Gemara might discuss which is
who violates בל יחל okay who gets the lashes? Is it all
about the status of the object or is it still about the
person who took the vow? And do you maybe need both of
those according to the רמב"ם Rambam in order to violate or is
and you know or certainly to get lashes or is just the
status what the focus is? Yes?
Would you say that that analysis and that distinction is similar to
the thinking in the first סוגיא sugya in שבת Shabbat with הוצאה?
hotza'ah?
Like when you take
two people the action's split in half.
Yeah no I wouldn't go there. That clearly focuses on the action
and the question is whether one person is doing it right. Here
the whole point is what is the status of the object and
you know independent of the issue of the taking of the vow.
So it's a yeah. Alright so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this top of ט"ו עמוד ב. Tet Vav Amud Bet. Okay.
תנן we're still getting back to the debate of רב נחמן and
רבי. Rebbi. Yehuda about whether we can trust you not to violate
the תנאי Tnai if you're already have violated the vow. Okay, שעטנז
לי על החג, Shaatnez li al hachag, so this is the reverse.
אם תלכי לבית אביך עד הפסח. Im telchi l'veit avich ad haPesach.
So here,
okay, you can't get הנאה all the way to סוכות, Succos, that's
the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah if and the תנאי Tnai is until
פסח. Pesach. So this is בית אביך, beit avich, this is the
תנאי, Tnai. and this is
whatever, thank you, this is the, I know, איסור הנאה issur hana'ah
for all those people, the visually oriented people among us. Fine, we'll
draw a little house.
Okay, when does the תקופה tekufah of עד הפסח ad haPesach start?
From the moment he takes the vow.
Okay, so don't get הנאה until סוכות Succos if you go to
your father's house עד הפסח. ad haPesach. Okay, so, okay, הלכה לפני
הפסח, halcha lifnei haPesach, אסורה בהנאה עד החג. asurah b'hana'ah ad hachag.
That's pretty obvious. If she goes before פסח, Pesach. she can't get
הנאה all the way until the חג. chag. ומותרת לילך אחר הפסח.
u'muteres leilech achar haPesach.
But presumably if she goes ahead
and goes to her father's house, yes, she can go to her
father's house after פסח, Pesach, which is like bizarre. Of course she
can go to her father's house after פסח. But like, so the
ראשונים Rishonim play out what the חידוש chiddush is. Maybe the חידוש
chiddush is just is that we're not afraid that if we let
her go to her father's house after פסח, somehow it'll lead to,
I don't know how retroactively here, but other cases or whatever, going
before פסח. Alright, that's a pretty obvious throwaway line. Alright, right, that
too. Okay, anyway, הלכה אסורה, halcha asurah, לא הלכה לא. lo halcha
lo. So it basically says if she goes, that's when we say
don't get הנאה. But if she doesn't go, we will trust her
to get הנאה and trust her to keep her תנאי. tnai Okay,
that's what it sounds like again. So we can trust her to
keep her תנאי. tnai. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא הלכה לא.
lo halcha lo. So it's going to give the same answer. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, no, הוא הדין אפילו לא הלכה אסורה. hu hadin
afilu lo halcha asurah. Even if she hasn't gone to her father's
house, we don't get הנאה until at least פסח.
הוא הדין אפילו לא הלכה אסורה. hu hadin afilu lo halcha asurah.
הלכה, Halcha, if she's already triggered the תנאי, tnai אסורה ולוקה, asurah
v'loka, then if she were to get הנאה now, either she would
get lashes or he would get lashes. We'll read it like the
ר"ן, Ran she'll get lashes
because now she's clearly in the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah because she's
triggered the תנאי. tnai לא הלכה, lo halcha, if she has yet
to go and it's this period before פסח, so אסורה בעלמא, asurah
b'alma, don't do it, but you're not going to get lashes. We
don't know what's going to happen in terms of the תנאי. tnai,
Okay, so just because it says once the תנאי tnai. is triggered,
she can't get הנאה, that means that that's when the full weight
of the prohibition has like, you know, has kicked in. But but
even before the תנאי tnai has triggered, it's not clear that we
would allow her to get הנאה. We might not allow her. We
might not be able to trust that she will be able to
keep to the תנאי. Okay. Again, that's not the פשט. pshat. The
פשט pshat of the משנה is against רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda The
פשט pshat of the משנה is is that as long as the
תנאי isn't triggered, she can go get go ahead and get הנאה
and we'll just trust her not to trigger the תנאי. But the
גמרא's Gemara reading it that no, that maybe she's forbidden either way.
It's just that she doesn't get lashes, you know, until the תנאי
has been triggered. Only if she violates after the תנאי has been
triggered. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי, Meisivei, another
case. כיכר זו עלי היום אם אלך למקום פלוני למחר. Kikar zo
alai hayom im eilech l'makom ploni l'machar.
This loaf of bread is forbidden to me today if I, you
know, go to Philadelphia tomorrow. Alright. So אכל, Achal, if I ate
this loaf of bread, הרי זה בבל ילך, harei zeh b'val eilech,
then I better not go to Philadelphia tomorrow. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara, says, it's funny, you gotta love that phrase, הרי זה בבל
ילך, harei zeh b'val eilech, like בבל יאכל, b'val ye'achel, like now
there's a new biblical prohibition: don't go to Philadelphia, which I've just
created. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מי קתני, mi katani, ah,
so you see that it seems like no problem eating it, just
don't don't trigger your תנאי. So the גמרא Gemara says, it didn't
say no problem eating it. מי קתני אוכל? mi katani ochel? It
doesn't say you're allowed to eat it. אכל קתני. achal katani. It
means if you ate it, now you better be careful. דכי אכל
הרי זה בבל ילך. d'chi achal harei zeh b'val eilech.
Okay. But you shouldn't have eaten it in the first place, but
if you've eaten it, now you'd really better be careful. Okay, now,
הלך, Halach, now it says like this, if I actually did go
to Philadelphia tomorrow, הרי זה בבל יאכל harei zeh b'val ye'achel retroactively
I've transgressed בל יאכל. bal ye'achel. דאורייתא. So any so so the
גמרא gemara. so, okay, presumably because I actually ate from it today.
So the גמרא gemara says, מהלך לא. mahalech lo. So it sounds
like I'm not לכתחילה lechatchila
allowed to go. Now, of course לכתחילה lechatchila I'm not allowed to
go, okay, because I ate the darn thing today. So, but it
says like this, according to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, what would רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda have told me to do? רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
would have told me... Don't eat this loaf of bread today because
I won't trust you to go tomorrow, I won't trust you to
keep it tonight tomorrow. So according to him, the default case was
that I didn't eat the loaf of bread today, so according to
him, I should be allowed to go to Philadelphia tomorrow because if
I was listening to him, I didn't eat the loaf of bread
today. Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. מהלך לו, mahalach lo,
it says, why doesn't it just say go to Philadelphia tomorrow? Why
does it say don't go? If you go you'll transgress. It assumes
you were
okay, you were eating the bread today. וקשיא לרב יהודה, v'kashya l'Rav
Yehuda, it's a question to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda אמר לך רב
יהודה, amar lach Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה will say בדיעבד, b'diavad, הוא
הדין דליסתני מהלך. hu hadin d'listani mahalach. It really could have said,
you know, you can go tomorrow, presuming that you're not going to
eat today. אלא איידי דתנא רישא אכל, ela ayadi d'tana reisha achal,
but since we set up the case, the first case, that you
actually did eat the loaf of bread, I didn't want you to
eat it, but you went ahead and ate it, right?
Therefore, דלא מיסתני ליה אוכל, d'lo mistani leh ochel, because it wasn't
able to say you're allowed to eat, because I say, says רב
יהודה, you're not allowed to eat. So therefore we started the case
by talking not about, you know, not about whether you are or
aren't allowed to eat, we started the case talking about the default,
assuming you weren't listening to us anyway and you just went ahead
and ate the loaf of bread. Once that's the case that you
went ahead and ate the loaf of bread, then we're going to
say,
where were we? תני סיפא הלך. tani seifa halach. Therefore we're going
to say that you went ahead and went, what will retroactively it
have done to your action? But we are never, you can't infer
that you were allowed or not allowed to eat at the outset.
We're not talking about whether you were or weren't allowed to eat.
We were talking that you had already eaten the loaf of bread,
what the consequence would be. So the גמרא Gemara is not clear
what the מסקנא maskana is, whether we will allow you to violate
your תנאי and trust you not, violate your נדר and trust you
not to violate your תנאי. At least a lot of the ראשונים
assume, since the גמרא, Gemara you know, it's always that funny thing.
The גמרא's Gemara going, working so hard to try to challenge a
particular position, רב יהודה's position, doesn't it mean we don't go like
רב יהודה because all the prima facie evidence is against him? Or
do we say since the גמרא's Gemara working so hard to make
him work, therefore it's trying to say that we do go like
him? Anyway, the ר"ן Ran? is inclined to go like רב יהודה
and would say that we, if you made a תנאי that we
don't yet know whether or not it'll be fulfilled, we're going to
tell you right now,
don't transgress the נדר out of a concern that you will trigger
the תנאי later on.
But this נדר with the loaf of bread that was eaten, the
נדר was made after you ate the loaf of bread?
No, before.
I won't eat, נדר this loaf of bread is אסור assur to
me if I go to Philadelphia tomorrow. So can I go ahead
and eat this loaf of bread and trust myself not to go
to Philadelphia? Right. Okay.
So then what's the whole point of if he eats the loaf
of bread?
Don't go to Philadelphia. Everybody would hold in that case you better
not go to Philadelphia. What's the punishment? No, no, you don't get,
no, retroactively you don't. That would be retroactive. There's no way you
can get lashes because we're only going to figure it out retroactively.
Okay. That's what the whole point of this משנה was. בל יחל
as opposed to לוקה. Okay? לוקה is you've already triggered the תנאי,
we know you're violating, you get lashes. בל יחל is when you
did it, you might violate it based on the תנאי. We find
out later that you violated it, then retroactively we know you violated
it, that's בל יחל without lashes. The question is, do we let
you now get הנאה and trust you to keep to the תנאי
tomorrow? Okay. What's the punishment?
What's the punishment? If he eats it today and goes to Philadelphia
tomorrow?
Then it's between him and God, you know,
right. Right. I mean, look, you got to step back and appreciate
this phenomenon, which is, in addition to the fact that it gives
us interesting, like, you know, תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, you know, ideas
to play with, you know, this is a way in which you
use a נדר which is about an object to address actions, right?
So rather than take a שבועה, I don't want to take a
שבועה because it's a שבועת שוא, shvuat shav, שבועת שקר, shvuat sheker,
לא ינקה השם את אשר ישא את שמו לשוא. lo yenakeh Hashem
et asher yisa et shemo lashav. You know, there's even greater hesitation
with שבועות shvuot than there is with נדרים. So what I'll do
is, how do I get myself to do or not do something?
What I'll do is I'll say, like, all fruit in the world
should be forbidden to me if I do X or if I
don't do X. And because I don't want to suffer the consequences
of the נדר, I'm going to force me to do or to
not do something. That's how you get the נדר to translate into
action, right? Because I don't want to have to deal with those
consequences. So let's say, I don't know, let's say I'm really trying
to make sure that I make that trip to Philadelphia, okay? So
but that trip isn't coming up for a week, right? So I
guess if I wanted to make things simpler, I would say if
I don't make that trip to Philadelphia, then at that point כל
פירות kol peirot should be אסור assur to me, okay? But I
complicated things a little bit and I didn't say that, and I
said כל פירות kol peirot אסור assur to me if I don't
make, to take that trip that I've been meaning to take. So
now we're in this weird twilight zone right now, right? Because we
don't know whether or not it'll kick in. But again, the phenomenon
is a very natural phenomenon. It's using נדרים to, you know, to
push yourself to do or
to not do certain
things. It's giving her the prerogative to act or not. Right.
Right. That's a good point too. That's a good point too. Yeah.
Okay. Yeah.
Okay, if,
if you can't אסור assur a חפץ chefetz
on
somebody else unless it's yours, then how can you אסור an action
on somebody?
You're not- where are you אסור-ing an action? What do you mean?
In the case with with the going to your father's house.
No, no again, that's how you do it through an object. If
you- I'm not forbidding you to go to your father's house. You're-
you're be my guest, go to your father's house. But the consequence
will be that if you do, then then I'm forbidding on you
any הנאה you'll get from me. So the- what I'm forbidding on
you is my thing, my הנאה, whether it's my body, right, whether
it's my body, whether it's my food, whether it's my car, my
house. All of that is forbidden to you. You're free to choose
whether or not to go to your father's house, but here are
the consequences. Okay. All right. So, yes.
Is he allowed to, what's it called?
Ah, excellent. That is the next גמרא. Gemara האומר לאשה Ha-omer l'isha
to our משנה, קונם שאני משמשך Konam she-ani mishamshech
הרי זה בבל יחל דבריו. harei zeh bivyal yachel dvarav. If the
man said to his wife, קונם Konam that I won't have sex
with you, so again, now we're not- it could be my body
is forbidden regarding sex, but we're talking here, we just said that
the משנה is about the דרבנן, so we're talking about the abstraction,
not actually the physical body, but the הנאה of the act of
sex that I would, you know, have with you is forbidden on
you. So he's forbidding that הנאה. Okay. So then it's בבל יחל.
So the גמרא Gemara says, how's he able to do that? והא
משתעבד לה מדאורייתא, V'ha mishtabed lah mid'oraita,
he has- he's biblically indebted to her, דכתיב as it says, שארה
כסותה ועונתה לא יגרע. Sh'erah ksutah v'onatah lo yigra.
He cannot withhold her food, clothing, and sex, and, you know, conjugal
relations and his obligation of marital sex. So now the question is,
who cares? Meaning, I- just because you have an obligation,
I can say, you know, all תפילין tefillin is אסור on me,
קונם Konam all תפילין tefillin on me, קונם all סוכות sukkahs on
me. And as we said, it works, because you know, because- because
it's only indirectly undermining my מצוה mitzvah obligation. It makes the object
forbidden and then I come to do the מצוה mitzvah and I
can't do it because the object is forbidden. So what's the big
deal? Yes, he has an obligation to have sex with his wife,
but he makes himself forbidden and then it indirectly undermines- he didn't
say I'm not going to have sex, he just made himself forbidden.
It's so to- as it were the object is forbidden, but he
didn't directly confront it. So the key here is not because he
has an obligation. That would not be enough. You have a מצוה
mitzvah obligation and you can make a נדר. The key is that
he has- he's משתעבד לה. mishtabed lah. She has, as it were,
a lien on his body, you know, she has rights to having
sex with him. Okay, this is actually an interesting whole legal question
or like church law as well because it had this whole idea
of conjugal rights but it's in הלכה, halacha, is it a חוב
hov or a חיוב? hiyuv? Right? Is it a personal obligation or
is it a debt? Is it like the woman has liens and
rights and some type of property ownership on the man in this
regard or does he have a מצוה mitzvah to do it?
So the language is קידושין- kidushin right- right, so
משתעבד לה mishtabed lah means he actually has- she actually has rights,
property rights as it- almost on him, you know, for that demand
of- for sex. And therefore when he tries to forbid the sexual
pleasure on her, he's not forbidding his thing on her, he's forbidding
her thing on her. You can't do that to me, I've got
rights on this- on your property, right? So if let's say we
jointly owned a car and you wanted to say my car is
forbidden to you, I get- it's an interesting question about שותפות shutafut
and we'll get to it, but it's like who are you to
forbid you know this thing on me? I've got rights to it,
okay? Let's say I rented your car, can you go ahead- I've
got your rental car for the rest of the week and you
could say that car is forbidden to you? What are you talking
about? I've got rights to it, I've rented it for the week.
Okay. So therefore, how is she in a position- that's the issue.
The issue is not obligation, but it's ownership. And therefore, since she
is considered like an ownership on his body or on his sexual
pleasure that he has the rights to for him, he cannot make
it forbidden. The language of the ר"ן Ran is, and the language
of the ר"ן is-
where's the ר"ן? I'm looking at רש"י. Rashi. The language of the
ר"ן is ועמיתא דמשתעבד לה. V'amita d'mishtabed lah. Wait a minute,
I'm just going to skip to the line.
He says like this, he says like this, he says הכא נמי,
hacha nami,
it's like four lines before the lines get wide at the beginning
of the line. דלא מצי עביד dlo matzi avid דמדאורייתא משעבד לה
dmideoraisa meshubed lah והוי כאוסר נכסי חבירו על חבירו vehavei keoser nichsei
chavero al chavero
When he tries to make his sexual pleasure forbidden on her, it's
hers and he's like trying to make his friend's fruit forbidden on
the friend. Okay, this is his, his wife has rights to this.
He can't make it forbidden. So back to the גמרא okay, ובאומר
beomer okay
here's how it works: הנאת תשמישך עלי hana'as tashmishech alay
I'm not going to make my sexual pleasure forbidden on you, says
the man to the woman, I'm going to make your sexual pleasure
forbidden on me. So therefore I can make your fruit forbidden to
me, so I can make your sexual pleasure, the sexual pleasure I
would get from you, says the husband to his wife, forbidden on
me. So you don't need ownership because you're making it forbidden on
yourself, not forbidden on somebody else, right? So I can make your
car forbidden to me, I can make your sexual pleasure forbidden on
me. Now indirectly it prevents him from doing his obligation, but as
we said, that's not a problem with נדר By a שבועה you
cannot directly obligate yourself against the pre-existing obligation, okay, but here it's
indirect. The sexual pleasure is forbidden on him, that works because you
can make anybody's thing forbidden on you. Now it comes time for
him to do the מצוות עונה mitzvas onah and he can't do
it because the, because the thing is forbidden. Not the act is
forbidden, as it were, the object is forbidden. Okay, so that kicked
in. Now of course they can't stay married that way, they'll have
to get a divorce, but the נדר takes effect,
okay. ובאומר הנאת תשמישך עלי beomer hana'as tashmishech alay so גמרא says
והא לא קני ליה בתשמיש veha lo kani lei betashmish and he
doesn't want or, not want, but now he's not able to have
sex. דאמר רב כהנא Damar Rav Kahana and now as we'll see
in the reverse: תשמישי עליך tashmishi alecha she says,
my sexual pleasure is forbidden on you. כופין אותה ומשמשתו kofin oso
umeshamashto She's not entitled to do that, she has to go ahead
and have sex with him, okay, because same idea. The same way
she has rights on his body to have sex and the husband
can't, you know, can't make his sex for, you know, his sexual
pleasure forbidden to her, she has rights to that, the same is
reverse. He has rights on, you know, to have sexual pleasure with
his wife, as it were on his body, and therefore she also
cannot make it forbidden on her husband. It doesn't, whatever, not by
force, but you basically, anyway,
it doesn't mean כופין לפתח kofin lepesach we had that before.
No, no, no. Anyway, no it doesn't mean that.
דשיבודי משעבדא ליה deshibudei meshubada lei She,
her body, as it were, is משועבד meshubed to him, but again,
now that of course woman as sexual property, right, and you know,
it's always been woman as sexual property, not man as sexual property,
you know, for millennia that's been the whole issue, right? And you
know, and but nevertheless what's important to note here is that the
גמרא actually started with the reverse, right? It wasn't just that the
husband had an obligation, it very much was a property rights in
the reverse as well. She had a type of a property rights
on his body and he could not make his הנאה forbidden, that
was her thing, right? Her rights to him was hers and he
could not make it forbidden. And similarly she cannot make his, you
know, her sex forbidden to him because he has rights to it.
Okay,
however if she said הנאת תשמישך עלי hana'as tashmishech alay
the sexual pleasure I would derive from you, she says to her
husband, is forbidden to me, you don't need property rights, you're making
it forbidden on yourself. In that case אסור she's forbidden to have
sex, שאין מאכילין לו לאדם דבר האסור לו she'ein machilin lo leadam
davar ha'assur lo You don't make somebody do something that they're not
allowed to have, they're not allowed to get that benefit. So they
would have to somehow get a divorce, okay. But this is a
very important גמרא You know, again, here we're getting it in מסכת
נדרים Masechet Nedarim but it's a critical גמרא in terms of thinking
about the sort of parallel, you know, questions about like rights of
sex and is so, is it a parallel or non-parallel relationship, right,
in terms of, in terms of the husband's right to have sex
with his wife and the wife's right to have sex with her
husband. Normally we focus on the מצווה mitzvah שאר כסות ועונה לא
יגרע she'er ksus veonah lo yigra
which it's his מצווה mitzvah to have sex with her. But a
מצווה is different than a right and we never fully spell out
what is, what's, you know, what's his, you know, what's his right
to have sex with her. We say that, did I missay that?
שאר כסות ועונה לא יגרע she'er ksus veonah lo yigra
is her right to, or his מצווה to have sex, and her,
you know, maybe like her right to demand sex with her husband
or whatever at regular intervals. We never sort of focus on the
reverse, which is his right to have sex with his wife, you
know, and is that a balanced or is that an unbalanced thing?
Is it a personal obligation, is it a debt? So this גמרא
is very important that it sort of brackets the significance of his
מצווה and focuses on that sense of an equal and parallel right
that one spouse has on the other. other, you know, in terms
of the, in terms of sexual relations. Okay, and because of that,
one spouse cannot make forbidden on the other their sexual pleasure on
the other person, because the other person actually has rights to that,
and it really just works out in terms of making somebody else's
pleasure forbidden on you. Okay, so very important again, not even so
much for נדרים, but conceptually thinking about, you know, the sort of
sexual, or the rights to sex of one partner on the other,
that in a society which is sort of very patriarchal and a
woman as sexual property of the man, that our סוגיא actually starts
by positing, by putting out there the reverse, that the man is
also sexual property of the wife, you know, within the marriage. And
the same, it uses the exact same language. She has a שעבוד
shibud on him, and he has a שעבוד shibud on her. So,
very important in terms of conceptually how we think הלכה halacha deals
with the issue of marital sex, you know, is, comes up through
this גמרא here in נדרים. Okay.